A Guide to the Papers of John Lothrop Motley, 1857-1876
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Lothrop Motley 1857-1876
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8065
21 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on December 17, 1963, accessioned on October 21, 1965, and changed to a gift on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 21 items, chiefly correspondence of John Lothrop Motley.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series. Series I contains a manuscript, and Series II contains letters.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Preface to The Life and Death of John Barneveld 1873 Oct 30, AMsS.
    9 handwritten pages one side only, bound with printed preface; printed preface with title page of Vol. I; 10 pages print (5 pages on 2 sides).
- Series II: Letters
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Edward] Everett 1857 Aug 11 [8?], ALS, 2p.
    Thanks Mr. Everett for letters of introduction to Lord Clarendon, Sir Henry Holland, and Mr. Dallas.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Robert Von] Mohl 1859 Jun 23, ALS, 2p.
    John Lothrop Motley sends information on the editions, translations and reprints of his book of the Dutch Republic; mentions Mr. Mignet and Madame Mohl.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [James Anthony] Froiude 1863 Jan 16, ALS, 4p.
    John Lothrop Motley sends two sonnets by Robert Lytton asking that they be published in Fraser's Magazine; comments on the American Civil War; mentions Robert Lowell and Atlantic Monthly and James Mill.
  - John Lothrop Motley to F. S. Grand d'Huateville 1864 Mar 1, ALS, 4p.
    Writes that he is unable to send the Emperor's autograph as requested for the fair by Mrs. Fish due to the extreme formal relationship of the diplomatic corps to the count in Austria; his wife and daughters have sent Vienna specialties; will attempt to get Goethe's autograph for Mrs. Fish.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Edmund] Quincy 1864 Aug 7, ALS, 8p.
    Writes on the death of Quincy's father, Josiah Quincy, with much praise on his life and deeds; makes a comparison with Lord Lyndhurst relative to statue [status/stature] and clarity of mind in old age; comments on Civil War; urges Edmund to write biography of Josiah.
  - John Lothrop Motley to L[ucius] Stebbins 1866 Jul 30, ALS, 2p.
    Writes that his official duties and private occupations make it impossible for him to write a history of the recent war in Europe as suggested.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Messrs. Harper Brothers 1864 Mar 19, ALS, 3p.
    Introduces John Lothrop Motley's nephew J. Lewis Stackpole who will have charge of all his business affairs while he is away from home and specifically for publication of the two concluding volumes of The History of the United Netherlands; thanks for publication of kind and flattering notice of John Lothrop Motley and book in Harper's Weekly; comments: Colonel Stackpole was son of John Lothrop Motley's deceased best friend Joseph Lewis Stackpole]
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Henry Wadsworth] Longfellow 1867 Aug 6, ALS, 1p.
    Introduces Viscount Amberley, eldest son of Earl Russell, and Lady Amberley who will visit the United States soon.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [John] Murray 1867 Sep 17, ALS, 3p.
    Writes concerning numbering of chapters in volumes III and IV of his history and inclusion of portraits of Barneveld and Maurice; mentions artist Cornelius Visscher.
  - John Lothrop Motley to General Adam Badeau 1868 Oct 26, ALS, 4p.
    Sends copies of his address in pamphlet form and requests that he present one to General Grant; mentions General Badeau's history of the Vicksburg and Chattanooga campaigns and forthcoming history of Richmond campaign; also mentions Crimean War.
  - John Lothrop Motley to General Adam Badeau 1869 Apr 15, ALS, 1p.
    Writes concerning breakfast and meeting about "business of importance" with General Badeau.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Hon. J. Russell Jones 1870 Sep 23, ALS, 2p.
    Writes concerning message for Brig. Gen. Hazen concerning permission to visit the Prussian Army.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Charles Keating Tuckerman] 1873 Jul 13, ALS, 3p.
    Writes to thank Tuckerman for sending the details of his conversation with Mr. Seward regarding the termination of Motley's mission to Vienna; mentions working on manuscript.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Messrs. Harper Brothers 1874 Mar 16, ALS, 3p.
    Sends corrections for Vol. II of The Life and Death of John Barneveld.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Mr. Mason 1875 Aug 17, ALS, 3p.
    Thanks Mr. Mason for his kind words; written in pencil.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Miss Jacobson 1876 May 20, ALS, 1p.
    Sends autograph and expresses pleasure that she enjoyed the History of the Dutch Republic.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Lady Dorothy [Nevill] [1876?] Sep 22, ALS, 4p.
    Sends information about visiting "House in the Woods" and the Queen when she visits the Netherlands.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Miss [Anne Isabella] Thackeray n.y. Nov 28, ALS, 1p.
    Regrets that due to his health he cannot visit with Mr. Carlyle as he had hoped.
  - John Lothrop Motley to Mrs. Webster n.d., ALS, 1p.
    Asks that he be excused for his abrupt disappearance from the Abbey due to his need to be home before the end of the service; left message with Lady Augusta.
  - John Lothrop Motley to [Edmund] Quincy n.d., ALS, 1p.
    Invites Quincy to dinner on Sunday next with G. W. Curtis and others.